So it seems very rare
um
that people
pick up the practice and take it
all the way.
And I'm wondering whether it takes a
certain type of character
to practice the Dhamma.
Well, it doesn't take like uh
I don't know, one of the 16 personality
traits or something.
Um character doesn't mean like um
Yeah, the random
personality habits that you have built
up over your life.
Uh what you need to have to practice the
Dhamma, well, the the Buddha mentioned
it like multiple times.
Um
one of the most important ones would be
somebody who
sees themselves or is like actively
looks for their shortcomings
rather than tries to cover them up.
Or looks for their what they or
not necessarily shortcomings, but like
things that they can still improve
over the things that, you know, they
feel confident about.
Um because
there's that sutta where the Buddha says
thinking that you understand what you
don't understand.
Um
uh being that kind of
conceited attitude that like you can't
accept that your world view needs to
change. That your values need to change.
That your values need to change.
That the values you currently have are
the ones are the reason why you suffer.
Um that whole
willingness to accept that.
And and like practice it. Not just a one
time I accept it and then, you know, I
just live the same way. But actually you
you you're going to have to
actively evolve.
Um so absence of complacency basically
is the number one character trait that
you need to have. Non-contentment with
uh wholesome or good or thing things
that you think are good.
Uh
you look for you see the glass half
empty rather than half full as the
saying goes.
And um
then the other one would be um
well, bravery. Like, you know, uh
recognizing cuz
cuz
when you don't have courage, when you
don't have bravery, um
you will either
not practice, give up the practice cuz
it's too hard, or you would try to mold
the practice into what you want it to
be. So that so that you don't have to
face the things that actually are
involved in the practice.
Um so
yeah, that's the second one. Like
recognizing, being able to
uh see that something is very difficult
and still not feel daunted.
Still realize and not lose perspective
that it factually has to be done.
Like, you know, how even in worldly
terms, some people
uh you know, there may be some
thing that has to be fixed. Let's say uh
construction project or something. And
it's like pretty bad if you don't fix
it. But for them, the discomfort of
But for them, the discomfort of
recognizing that this has to be done is
so big that they actually don't do it.
Rather than, you know, prioritizing the
the perception of harm
of what's going to happen cuz that's a
absence of that uh you could say
courage. So that uh it's not a blind, like you
So that uh it's not a blind, like you
you you
you're chasing after difficulty as a
kind of um
to to to get a kick out of it. It's like
the things that are factually difficult
already and at the same time need to be done,
and at the same time need to be done,
you're not uh afraid of holding those
two ideas together. So,
So,
but it's not
um
Say someone tries to imagine that
what someone who is courageous is like,
like they might I imagine someone who is
already full of courage
and even though the even though
something seems
uh impossible,
they're not phased or daunted by it. Hm.
And so, in that sense, it's kind of I
must be easy for them. Right. No, but
the thing is
uh that doesn't come from
like if it's easy for them,
it's not because of a random fate thing,
it's because let's say if you don't have
it, you have been actively cultivating
you have been actively cultivating
habits in the opposite direction
that you can equally
you have to uh undo
by, for example,
it's all a matter of like when those
situations come up, difficult
situations, you have the chance to think about why
you have the chance to think about why
it still has to be done.
You have a chance of reflecting on
all the bad things that are going to
happen if you don't do it, but you
choose not to
because it's more comfortable to to just
uh not do it and not and not accept that
it should be done.
So, if at least you
are able to maintain the the clarity
that it should be done,
and you don't try to uh obscure that in
order to not feel guilty,
then you are like you you've at least
walked through the door, so to speak.
Because then you will have the
the the the ability to at some point
like start doing it. But the opposite
option where like you you don't accept
that it has to be done,
then even if you don't feel guilty, even
if you feel completely at peace,
that entire peace is wrong.
Cuz it's the peace of delusion.
So it's actually more important to be
aware of how things actually are, like
the the danger of
uh sickness, aging, death,
the peril that you are subjected to by
not freeing yourself from craving
because of all these calamities that are
going to come to you.
It's more accurate to be aware of that
and to to um
make that recollection a part of your
life than it is to be \ peaceful
by not thinking about those things.
Cuz that peace will only
increase the pain and the surprise and the the
the pain and the surprise and the the
burden that will come to you whenever
things get ruined, which will happen.
So it's a peace that's basically like um
it's like taking a loan, literally. Like
in the moment, you feel be feeling
better, but what's waiting for you at the end of
but what's waiting for you at the end of
that is much worse.
So it's like it you could say that's a
character trait, like that that somebody
prefers to
like non-procrastination, for example.
Like somebody prefers to
fix things when they're actually
important, not like you're trying to
find random work to do, but like
if something is actually important,
you tend to to uh uh uh uh uh uh
not rest
until you've done it.
>> It seems that
these are qualities of really putting
how you feel second. Mhm.
It's not That's not really part of the
picture in terms of the
your assessment of what you're you want
to do what you need to do. That's a
that's a character trait in itself, like
being able to
recognize that that um
you know, keep perspective of I need to
do this independently of how I feel.
But and that's actually something that
declines with time. Like in the average person,
with time. Like in the average person,
you can see that it pretty much goes in
the opposite direction, like
the more people proliferate their senses
and their their
um mundane delights, the more
difficult it is for them to do things
when they're painful.
Everything needs to be kind of covered
up in some
uh immediate benefit
in order to be doable.